Guide to the Louis Mayer Rabinowitz Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Louis Mayer Rabinowitz collection
1676-1957
MS 1044
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(1 box)
Correspondence, volumes, and other papers collected by Rabinowitz. Includes autograph letters of Henry Blackwell (1851-1928), Charles Darwin (1809-1882), Samuel Huntington (1731-1796), and Roger Sherman (1721-1793).
Rabinowitz, Louis M. (Louis Mayer), 1887-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Louis M. Rabinowitz, 1940s.
Scope and Contents
This autograph collection compiled by Louis M. Rabinowitz contains several letters by British and European notables such as Charles Darwin, a number of letters and documents signed by well-known Americans of the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, such as John C. Calhoun and Roger Sherman, and a Latin handbook of logic from the eigtheenth century, but the bulk of the collection is made up of papers of Henry Blackwell (1851-1928). Included are letters to Blackwell from a variety of individuals from Wales and elsewhere interested in Welsh history and literature, and two copies of Blackwell's bibliography of materials about Wales published in the United States, with a number of newspaper clippings found in the volumes. The letters were for the most part removed from books belonging to Blackwell which Rabinowitz donated to Yale University. The final item in the collection is a reminiscence of Rabinowitz by James T. Babb.
Additional printed and manuscript material has been given to the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library by Louis Rabinowitz. For a description of this material, the researcher should speak to the reference staff at the Beinecke Library.
Biographical / Historical
Manufacturer and philanthropist; born in Rossane, Lithuania; came to the United States in 1901; founded L.M. Rabinowitz & Co. in 1917 in New York City, served as president from 1917-1957; organized the Lamar Slide Fastener Co. and served as president, 1939-1954; known for his philanthropic gifts; in 1944 he established the Louis M. Rabinowitz Foundation; foundation inaugurated a research and publication program in Hebrew lore and literature at Yale.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Politicians -- Autographs; Autographs; Booker, Luke, 1762-1835; Calhoun, John C. (John Caldwell), 1782-1850; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882; Davies, John; Huntington, Samuel, 1731-1796; Sherman, Roger, 1721-1793; Tyler, John, 1790-1862
- Inventory, 1676-(1765-1915)-[1957]; 5" (1 box)
  - Autograph letters
    - Booker, Luke, 1762-1835: ALS to unidentified, removed from The Springs of Plynlimmon, 1834, by Rev. Luke Booker, belonging to Henry Blackwell, 1830 February 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Calhoun, John Caldwell, 1782-1850: ALS to John A. Calhoun, 1848 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Chapman, Mary Blackwell Sterling: ALS to Henry Blackwell, removed from Sir Thomas Malory, The Story of Sir Galahad…Retold by Mary Blackwell Sterling, c. [1908], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Columbia Publishing Company: TLS to Henry Blackwell, giving a brief history of Columbia, a weekly newspaper "published in the interest of the Welsh people and their descendants in the United States", 1892 January 28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Daniels, R T., d.1896: ALS to Henry Blackwell, giving the history of Y Wasg, the second Welsh newspaper published in Pittsburg, 1886 January 21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882: ALS to unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Davies, John: 3 ALS to Henry Blackwell, removed from The Celtic Element in the Dialects..., by John Davies, 1883 April 19, July 4, 1884 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Evans, Samuel J.: ALS to Henry Blackwell, removed from Studies in Welsh Phonology, 1909, 1910 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Furness, J R.: ALS to Henry Blackwell, removed from King Henry the VII, 1900, 1900 November 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Hadley, Alice: 2 ALS to Henry Blackwell, concerning the Conway parish register, which Hadley was preparing, 1900 May 15, 1903 January 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Haines, W.: ALS to Henry Blackwell, removed from An Account of the Presentation of the Colours…, by Charles Heath, 1913 December 19 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Halliday, George Eley: 2 ALS to Henry Blackwell, removed from Llandaff Church Plat e, 1901, 1909 March 29, 1910 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hathaway, Matthew: signed receipt issued to Roger Sherman, 1765 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hendrickson, Rev. Wm. H.: ALS to Henry Blackwell, 1903 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Horton, E M.: ALS to Henry Blackwell, concerning Rev. James Powell, 1889 August 14 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hughes, H. Seymour: 2 ALS to Henry Blackwell, removed from The Registers of Llantrithyd, Glamorganshire, 1888, 1888 October 18, 1889 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hughes, Joshua, bp. of St. Asaph, 1807-1889: ALS to Henry Blackwell, concerning Richard Robarts Jones ("Dick of Aberdaron"), 1883 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Humphreys, Daniel: signed receipt to Roger Sherman, 1765 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Humphreys, David, 1752-1818: ALS to James Monroe, with typed transcript, 1816 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Huntington, Samuel, 1731-1796
      - Commission to Theophilus Miles Smith as ensign of 5th Company, 2nd Regiment, Connecticut Militia, 1786 November 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Copy of letter to General Knox, 1791 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Commission to Jared Huntington as captain of 14th Regiment, Connecticut Militia, 1793 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Johnes, Thomas, 1748-1816: ALS to Charles Taylor, removed from An Attempt to Describe Hafod…, by George Cumberland, 1796, belonging to Henry Blackwell, 1802 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jones, Charles Colcock, 1831-1893: ALS to Henry Blackwell, removed from Button Gwinnett, by Charles C. Jones, 1884, 1886 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Leete, William, ca.1613-1683: LS to John Leverett, Governor of Massachusetts, and the Hon. Council with him at Boston, 1676 August 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Levick, James Jones, 1824-1893: ALS to Henry Blackwell, removed from John Ap Thomas and His Friends, 1884, 1884 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Lewis, Kinnersley: ALS to Henry Blackwell, removed from Hymn to the Eternal, 1886, 1888 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Matthews, T: 5 ALS to Henry Blackwell, removed from Welsh Records in Paris, 1910, 1910 May 5 - 1913 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Morgan, Thomas: ALS to Henry Blackwell, removed from Handbook of the Origin of Place-Names in Wales and Monmouthshire, 1887, 1888 January 9 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Morris, Edward Dafydd, 1825-1915: ALS to Henry Blackwell, 1910 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Powell, Ella J. (Mrs. James): 2 ALS to Henry Balckwell concerning her husband, 1889 August 19, October 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Pritchard, Emily M.: 2 ALS to unidentified, 1908 February 3, 26 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Sherman, Roger, 1721-1793: summons to Safford Stevens of Canaan, Connecticut, to appear before the County Court at New Haven, 1786 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Thomas, D R.: ALS to unidentified, 1888 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Thomas, Isaiah, 1749-1831
      - ALS to Messrs. Hudson and Goodwin, 1790 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - ALS to Isaac Beers, 1792 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Thomas, W. Glawthorne: ALS to Bishop of St. Asaph (Joshua Hughes), enclosed in ALS from Joshua Hughes to Henry Blackwell, 1883 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Tyler, John, 1790-1862: ALS to Dr. Sprague, 1860 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Vidocq, Eugène François, 1775-1857: ALS to M. le Prefet, removed from Vidocq's Mémoires, 1828, 1834 June 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Williams, Sir John, 1840-: ALS to Henry Blackwell, removed from An Address Delivered… Oct. 27, 1904, by Sir John Williams, 1915 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Williams, Richard
      - ALS to Henry Blackwell, with copy of Williams' title page to his Welsh translation of Bacon's Essays, removed from A History of the Parish of Llanbrynmair, 1889, 1890 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - 2 ALS to Henry Blackwell, removed from Montgomeryshire Worthies, 1884, 1890 July 22, 1904 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Volumes
    - Blackwell, Henry, 1851-1928: "Bibliography of What Has Been Published in the United States Relating to Wales and the Welsh from the Earliest to the Present Time"
      - Bound manuscript, 1886 February 22 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Bound typescript, 1886 February 22 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Logica, a handbook of logic in Latin, [18th century] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Other paper
    - Newspaper clippings in Welsh and English, removed from "Bibliography of What Has Been Published...", 1893-1914 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "Louis Mayer Rabinowitz," by James T. Babb, [1957] (Box 1, Folder 15)